<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-13T18:33:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A website about me, Clark Wakeland, and my thoughts on a whole lot of things. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Observations in swimming no one talks about</title><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2025/swimming-observations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Observations in swimming no one talks about"/><published>2025-01-07T18:57:41+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T18:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2025/swimming-observations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2025/swimming-observations/"><![CDATA[<ul> <li>Hyper specializing in one event leads to local maximums (instead of global)</li> <li>Recognizing a plateau in performance should prompt an immediate change of either training methods or stroke technique</li> <li>The coach-athlete dynamic on a high performing swim team is isomorphic to the manager-IC dynamic in a “real world” job. Managers, like coaches, can bring out the best of their team, and are often more responsible for the success of the team than the athlete/IC likes to think</li> <li>Past a certain point, diet optimization does not matter. Keep it simple and eat high quality food.</li> <li>Modern training philosophy still involves too much yardage, even for distance swimmers. This has changed in recent years but we can probably go even further.</li> <li>Swimming is more of a body kinematics problem than a fluid dynamics one.</li> <li>Team culture won’t directly make you faster, but it will make you enjoy training more, which gives you more opportunities to actually get faster.</li> <li>The best way to make a team better is to first maximize the quality of your individual contributions, i.e., get faster. After that, it becomes much easier to elevate and inspire the people around you.</li> <li>Choosing to swim all four years in college will put you behind in the first year of your professional engineering career from a technical and field specific knowledge standpoint. But it is worth it.</li> <li>Time trials are a fantastic way to go a best time.</li> <li>Very few people are good enough to not try in prelims.</li> <li>“Fly and die” is a terrible race strategy. Your goal should be making the front half feel as easy as possible.</li> <li>Every training regime will work well for at least one person work terribly for at least one other person. Find a program that seems to be working well for <em>most</em> (&gt;80%) people.</li> <li>The negative effects of partying come from disease transmission rather than excessive alcohol consumption.</li> <li>Cliques of four to six people will form on any team. This is totally normal and actually a good thing. Inter-clique relationships should be maintained at a high priority.</li> <li>Yes, you were actually just as green as new guys.</li> </ul> <p>Last updated: 2025-01-07</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Also relevant to engineering teams]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collaboration is the key to my productivity</title><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collaboration is the key to my productivity"/><published>2024-11-16T18:57:41+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-16T18:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p>“Peer Pressure” was the original phrase I used when writing this post, but that has too much negativity surrounding it. “Collaboration”, or maybe even “Accountability”, better represents the (healthy) desire to perform well for the sake of the people around you. I’ve found that working with other passionate people on something is incredibly engaging and generally the environment in which I find myself doing my best work.</p> <p>Like many engineers, I start solo projects and then abandon them halfway through or never even make it past the design phase. There are thousands of guides on the internet that offer productivity techniques like Pomodoro timers, Eating the Frog, and Getting Things Done. I’m sure that those work for a good amount of people, and I’m very happy they found a method that works for them. However, while I haven’t exhausted all of these techniques, none of them seem to bring me to the constant level of engagement I’ve had in the past with other projects.</p> <p>I did an exercise where I wrote down all the projects I was a part of where I considered myself engaged and looked for some kind of commonality between them. Working through the list, it became increasingly apparent that none of these were solo endeavors. Quite the opposite in fact. I was typically surrounded by highly qualified and passionate individuals, all of them contributing their own time and effort to the same objective. To give an example, I’ll go through the “project” I’ve had the most experience with: swimming at a high level.</p> <hr/> <p>I really enjoy swimming. And when I say that, I mean the physical action of moving through the water, as opposed to enjoying it for the competitive aspect. Jumping in a pool, the dynamic movements, being in a different medium than what you spend 95% of your life in. There’s just nothing else like it. While racing fast it’s own form of enjoyment, the point that I’m making is that I enjoy the <em>individual</em> experience of swimming very much.</p> <p>Despite this, I know from experience that swimming alone, and more specifically, <em>training</em> alone, is very much not fun. Anyone who claimed they could train at a high level on their own, without coaches, teammates, or any other trainers, I would think of as delusional. I’m not even talking about the task of constructing your own training regime. That part is pretty easy when you’ve been doing it long enough, and probably even better to do yourself (in some cases) to optimize for personal preferences. Rather, the consistency required to push yourself during every single practice is multiple orders of magnitude harder going solo than even with one or two more people. I would never think of a swimmer as lazy if they couldn’t train on their own, by themselves.</p> <p>Why should I treat other projects I work on any differently? It would be unreasonable for me to expect myself to train full time alone. Surely it would also be unreasonable to expect myself to pursue that Pokémon ROM hack alone, or finally get around to solo building that satellite ground station. Having even just one other person - a “training partner” - immensely reduces the activation energy needed to get to a flow state of work, and also helps with distributing tasks when the true scope of the project finally reveals itself (since humans are notoriously bad at estimating the complexity of a project).</p> <p>Of course, this leads to an unfortunate prisoner’s dilemma for self proclaimed introverts like myself. We recognize that collaboration is necessary to succeed, but the task of asking someone if they’re interested seems incredibly daunting - mainly due to fear of rejection. As a result, we end up in this defection death spiral where nobody is willing to ask anyone for collaboration on a project. This can lead to a romanticized view of solo projects where rejection is not possible. Similarly, if the project doesn’t go anywhere, then the cost was only your own time and not someone else’s - which (incorrectly) implies that your time is worth less than other people’s.</p> <hr/> <p>I took me a long time get out of this line of thinking. My best advice would be that the loss incurred by someone defecting is a lot smaller than you think. Trust me, they’re still going to be your friend, even if they’re not interested in learning ancient Greek-art deco fusion pottery with you. On the other hand, if the task generally covers topics that a potential partner is interested in, the odds they accept are higher than you think. And neither of you need to be at Olympic level equivalence in your craft to create something amazing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anecdotal advice on where I do my best work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winning the Bridge to Bridge swim</title><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/bridge-to-bridge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winning the Bridge to Bridge swim"/><published>2024-08-07T18:57:41+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-07T18:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/bridge-to-bridge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/bridge-to-bridge/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p><em>In primordial space, timeless creatures made waves. These waves created us and others. Waves were the battles, and the battles were the waves.</em> <br/><br/> – Marathon: Durandal</p> </blockquote> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col"></div> <div class="col-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ggate-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ggate-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ggate-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ggate.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Delusions and Grandeur" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col"></div> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-waves">The Waves</h2> <p>I’ve completed and now won my second swim in the SF Bay: a 10k from the Golden Gate Bridge to the Bay Bridge.</p> <p>This race was quite nice because instead of swimming in laps around buoys like a traditional open water race, most of the swim was <em>with</em> the current. The waves on the ocean side of the Golden Gate bridge were incredibly choppy, but immediately smoothed out on the bay side, as if passing into a sea of tranquility. Once we were in the water, it was a quick start. We were instructed to head towards Alcatraz at first and then make a sharp right towards the Palace of Fine Arts to catch the current above SF.</p> <p>I remember the moment I caught the current - it felt like I was body surfing. Aside from the supermassive container ship coming up behind me (which I heard before I saw), the swim was mostly uneventful. I had a fantastic view of the city skyline from the water. When I made it to the end, they hadn’t even put up the finish buoy yet. <br/><br/></p> <h2 id="the-battles">The Battles</h2> <p>I was less than four minutes off the course record, but didn’t have any strong feelings about not breaking it. I had felt sluggish in the pool for the past few days and honestly after about 20 minutes of the swim I felt more fatigue than expected in my upper body. I think my lack of full time training is finally catching up, but it’s a sacrifice I’m willing to make to not have to swim 20 hours a week.</p> <p>Breakfast afterwards at the Buena Vista Cafe near Aquatic Park in SF was the perfect conclusion.</p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col"></div> <div class="col-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/postSwim-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/postSwim-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/postSwim-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/postSwim.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="The water here was pretty questionable. I'm talking could-barely-see-my-hand-in-front of-me levels of murky" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col"></div> </div> <div class="caption"> Post swim, after the marine layer had burned off SF </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="swimming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A swim in the bay]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Magellan Swim Challenge</title><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/magellan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Magellan Swim Challenge"/><published>2024-06-01T18:57:41+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T18:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/magellan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/magellan/"><![CDATA[<script type="module" src="/assets/js/main.js"></script> <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2> <p>Ferdinand Magellan was a Portuguese explorer who embarked on a 1519 Spanish expedition with the goal of crossing the Atlantic and Pacific oceans and opening a trade route to present day Indonesia. The voyage is well known for being the first to circumnavigate the Earth. Although Magellan himself did not survive to complete the journey, his name is synonymous with global navigation, exploration, and human tenacity.</p> <p>Because of this, I introduce the epynomous Magellan Swim Challenge: swimming a distance approximately equal to the circumference of the Earth - 24,901 miles (40,075 km).</p> <p>In reality, Magellan’s expedition covered almost 60,000 miles. But for the sake of the challenge, I chose to set a number that represents the shear act of encircling the globe just by swimming. Plus, you can create a swim route that is nearly the same distance (if you’re alright with a quick swim through the Panama Canal).</p> <p>I’m not aware of anyone who has officially completed this yet, but I have a couple likely guesses: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beno%C3%AEt_Lecomte">Benoît Lecomte</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Strel">Martin Strel</a>.</p> <h2 id="personal-progress">Personal Progress</h2> <p>I did not officially record all the practices of my competitive swimming career, but I believe a very conservative estimate is 11,000 miles. As of July 2024, I belive I have swam</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <h3 id="distance">11365 miles</h3> </div> <p>in my life. On the interactive globe below, the green path represents the distance I have swam so far, and the red path represents the distance I have left to go. The overall path follows a hypothetical circumnavigation starting in the San Francisco Bay and crossing through the Panama Canal on the way back.</p> <div id="content-window" style="display: flex; justify-content: center; align-items: center; "> <canvas id="canvas_ID"></canvas> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="swimming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Swimming around the world]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introductions</title><link href="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introductions"/><published>2024-05-29T18:57:41+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T18:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://clarkwakeland.github.io/blog/2024/intro/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to Threading Water, a blog about swimming, engineering, and the surprising intersections I’ve found between them. I’ll cover topics including but not limited to: competitive swimming, my experience in the aerospace industry, and the lessons I’ve learned in both of them. Most of the statements and examples in these posts will be purely anecdotal, but I’ll reference sources whenever possible. Most posts involving training techniques or mentality will be about swimming but can be applied to any sport or craft someone is trying to master.</p> <p>The blog has multiple goals:</p> <p>First, I want to share the thoughts in my head rather than leave them internalized. I’ve found out that keeping ideas to yourself, even if you think they’re not great in the moment, can actually lead to missed opportunities, slower progress, and suboptimal solutions to problems you’re encountering. This blog is an attempt to change that personal policy I’ve found myself following for too long.</p> <p>Second, I believe that my background in swimming and engineering has provided me with unique blend of insights. The overlap of highly competitive swimmers and passionate engineers is (unsurprisingly) not very large, yet I find myself applying ideas I learned in one domain to other all the time.</p> <p>Finally, I want to help people think in different ways. I spent this past winter volunteering as a teacher for high school students, and the satisfaction I felt when I saw a student gain an understanding of concept by approaching it in a new way was amazing. If even just one person were to read these posts and learn something valuable, I would consider that an overwhelming success.</p> <p>My hope is that someone somewhere will be able to take away something from these posts. If you have any comments or suggestions please feel free to reach out by <a href="mailto:clark.wakeland7@gmail.com">email</a> or any of the social sites listed in the <a href="/">about</a> page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An introduction to Threading Water]]></summary></entry></feed>